# Alexander Giovannelli

Phone: +1-740-258-9709Email: agiovannelli@vt.edu Site: https://agiovannelli.github.io/

## $\operatorname{Summary}$

My research interest lies in the intersections of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Augmented/Virtual Reality (AR/VR), and 3D User Interfaces (3DUI) for collaboration. I am exploring how to improve asynchronous collaborative processes using immersive technologies. Specifically, I am prototyping and evaluating systems that capture collaborator actions, providing supplemental visuals and interactive mechanisms for future playback.

## EDUCATION

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA

Ph.D. in Computer Science advised by Doug A. Bowman, GPA: 4.00/4.00 Aug. 2021-Present

University of Cincinnati Cincinnati, OH, USA

B.S. in Computer Engineering with German Studies minor, GPA: 3.30/4.00 Aug. 2013-May 2018

## SKILLS

Programming Languages: C#, JavaScript, Java, Python, HTML, CSS

Productivity Tools: Unity, Git, JMP, SPSS, LaTeX, Tableau

## Research Experience

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA Spring 2023 & Fall 2023 Graduate Research Assistant

- Investigated methods for asynchronous and synchronous collaboration in immersive experiences
- Performed contextual inquiry and analysis to determine research goals
- Created prototype virtual reality applications using C# and Unity technologies

#### Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

Livermore, CA, USA

Computing Research Intern

Summer 2023

- Developed guided tour prototypes for inspection processes in virtual reality using C# and Unity technologies
- Facilitated meetings between multi-disciplinary project stakeholders
- Prepared user study procedure for evaluation of prototype capabilities

Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA, USA Summer 2022

Graduate Research Assistant

- Conducted research regarding communication via avatars in augmented and virtual reality

- Generated prototype applications and experimental studies using C# and Unity technologies
- Designed and administered user studies in accordance with Institutional Review Board regulations

## Work Experience

#### JPMorgan Chase & Co.

Columbus, OH, USA Jul. 2018-Jul. 2021

Associate Software Engineer I

- Developed front-end features for Chase.com using JavaScript, HTML, and CSS technologies

- Designed and implemented minimum viable product user interfaces via Figma design tool
- Authored technical documentation for product owners and developers
- Appointed subject matter expert in behavioral-driven development and CI/CD initiatives
- Automated logging of proprietary systems using the Python programming language

#### Siemens Healthineers

Forchheim, BY, DE

Software Engineer Intern

Jan. 2017-Aug. 2017

- Developed back-end software for use in advanced therapy devices using the C# programming language
- Created system architecture diagrams to record project design changes and behaviors
- Represented project team in international software integration meetings using German and English languages

#### Granville Exempted Village Schools

Granville, OH, USA

Systems Administrator Intern

May 2016-Jul. 2016

- Provisioned Windows and Linux server and workstation systems to support school network infrastructure
- Administered changes to proprietary devices regarding operating system applications, packages and images
- Managed summer technician team operations

#### Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

Aug. 2015–Dec. 2015

- Created full-stack internal software tools for engineers and project managers using C#, XML and SQL
- Updated existing project management software according to submitted user feedback
- Authored software usage documents to elaborate on internal tool usage

#### Matrix Technologies, Inc.

Maumee, OH, USA

Computer Programmer and Systems Analyst Intern

Aug. 2014-Dec. 2014

- Enhanced existing proprietary software using the C# programming language
- Researched emerging technologies and presented potential process improvements for development team
- Coordinated project design changes with stakeholders

#### Projects

• Test Environment for Precise Manipulation Tasks

Sept. 2023-Present

Development of existing codebase to provide a study-based execution of precise manipulation experimentation

• Guided Tours for Multiscale Collaborative Virtual Environments

Mar. 2023–Present

Design and prototyping of a virtual environment for collaboration in multiscale inspection processes

• CLUE: An Immersive Competitive Lock-Unlock Experience Development of a gamified experience for Metaverse security using token sequences as an authentication method

Nov. 2022-Mar. 2023

• Virtual Avatar Reaction Visualizations in VR Jun. 2022-Mar. 2023 Development of a virtual environment for user studies investigating avatar reaction visualizations in collaboration

• Surface Generation for MR Remote Collaboration

Jun. 2022-Sept. 2023

Prototyping and testing of multi-user environment for shared surface creation and collaboration

• Environment for Intermittent Typing Experiments in VR

Jan. 2022–May 2022

Creation of a virtual environment with mixed reality capabilities for conducting text-entry user studies

• Smart Lighting Design in Immersive VR

Jan. 2022–Apr. 2022

Development of methods and techniques to support smart real-time lighting design in virtual reality

Clean the Ocean: An Immersive VR Experience

Oct. 2021-Mar. 2022

Creation of a virtual reality experience implementing novel enhancements to classic 3D interaction techniques

## Peer Reviewed Journal Papers

1. **A. Giovannelli**, J. Thomas, L. Lane, F. Rodrigues, and D. A. Bowman, "Gestures vs. emojis: Comparing non-verbal reaction visualizations for immersive collaboration", to appear in *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics*, 2023.

## Peer Reviewed Conference Papers

- 2. F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Pavanatto, H. Miao, J. C. Oliveira, and D. A. Bowman, "Amp-it and wisdom: Improving 3d manipulation for high-precision tasks in virtual reality", to appear in 2023 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), 2023.
- 3. **A. Giovannelli**, L. Lisle, and D. A. Bowman, "Exploring the impact of visual information on intermittent typing in virtual reality", in 2022 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), 2022, pp. 8–17.

## Peer Reviewed Workshops, Posters, Abstracts, & Contests

- 4. I. A. Tahmid, F. Rodrigues, A. Giovannelli, L. Lisle, J. Thomas, and D. A. Bowman, "Colt: Enhancing collaborative literature review tasks with synchronous and asynchronous awareness across the reality-virtuality continuum", to appear in 2023 International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality Adjunct (ISMAR-Adjunct), 2023.
- 5. A. Giovannelli, F. Rodrigues, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, L. Lane, C. Connor, K. Davidson, G. N. Ramirez, B. David-John, and D. A. Bowman, "Clue hog: An immersive competitive lock-unlock experience using hook on go-go technique for authentication in the metaverse", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 945-946.
- 6. J. Thomas, S. W. Lee, **A. Giovannelli**, L. Lane, and D. Bowman, "A communication-focused framework for understanding immersive collaboration experiences", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 301–304.
- 7. L. Lisle, F. Lu, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, **A. Giovannelli**, C. Llo, L. Pavanatto, L. Zhang, L. Schlueter, and D. A. Bowman, "Clean the ocean: An immersive vr experience proposing new modifications to go-go and wim techniques", in 2022 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2022, pp. 920–921.
- 8. E. Mohammadrezaei, A. Giovannelli, L. Lane, and D. Gračanin, "A digital twin based approach to smart lighting design", in 2022 Winter Simulation Conference (WSC), 2022.

#### Awards

• I/ITSEC Leonard P. Gollobin Scholarship	2023
• Davenport Leadership Fellowship	2023 - 2024
• Honorable Mention for Best IEEE ISMAR 2022 Conference Paper [3]	2022
• Best 3DUI Contest Entry [7]	2022
• International Co-op Program Scholarship	2016 - 2017
• Matrix Technologies, Inc. Co-op Scholarship	2014-2016

#### Professional Service

• Communications Chair

Develop and moderate discussion platforms for the IEEE VR 2024 conference

• Student Volunteer 2023

	Assist in event operations at IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality 2023	
•	Student Volunteer	2023
	Assist in event operations at IEEE VR 2023 satellite event in Blacksburg, Virginia	
•	Student Volunteer	2022
	Assist in event operations at IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality 2022	
•	Member of Computer Science Graduate Student Council	2021-Present
	Represent the interests of the CS graduate student body and assist in event planning	
•	Member of the Center for Human-Computer Interaction	2021-Present
	Active participant in the Center seminars regarding the study of human-computer interaction	

## Teaching

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Comparative Languages (CS-3304)

 $\operatorname{Fall}\ 2022$ 

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Software Design & Data Structures (CS-2114) Fall 2021 & Spring 2022